Finding Aid for the Gardner Family Papers LSC.0759
UCLA Library Special Collections
Gardner Family papers
1877-1960
UCLA Library Special Collections
Gardner family
Gardner, Henri F.
Gardner, Dian Rathbun
LSC.0759
13.0 Linear Feet (12 boxes)
The Gardner family was important in the land development and citrus production of Orange County, California. His son, Dian Rathbun Gardner, was a attorney who helped establish the Gardner Company by the family heirs after the death of his mother, Emma Howard Gardner, in 1935. The company dissolved in 1961 following the death of Dian Rathbun Gardner. The collection consists of correspondence, clippings, legal material, and ephemera relating to Henri F. Gardner, his wife Emma H. Gardner, his son Dian Rathbun Gardner, and the Gardner Company of Orange, California. Also includes account books, bank statements, correspondence and stock certificates relating to water development in Orange County, employee records and files on citrus production of the Gardner Company.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dion L. Gardner 1962, 1970.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID:9914704853606533
Biography
The Gardner family was important in the land development and citrus production of Orange County, California; Henri F. Gardner, landowner and developer, also played a role in water development of the county during the late 19th and early 20th centuries; his son, Dian Rathbun Gardner, was an attorney who helped establish the Gardner Company by the family heirs after the death of his mother, Emma Howard Gardner, in 1935; the company dissolved in 1961, following the death of Dian Rathbun Gardner.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, clippings, legal material, and ephemera relating to Henri F. Gardner, his wife Emma H. Gardner, his son Dian Rathbun Gardner, and the Gardner Company of Orange, California. Includes over 100 land deeds, leases, and rental agreements from 1874-1918, Henri Gardner's daily journals for the 1880s, and papers dealing with the estate of Emma Howard Gardner. Also includes account books, bank statements, correspondence and stock certificates relating to water development in Orange County, employee records and files on citrus production of the Gardner Company.
Expanded Scope and Content
This collection contains materials on land development and citrus production in Los Angeles and Orange counties. It is divided into three sections: 1) The papers of Henri of Henri F. Gardner (1852-1918), land owner and developer, ca. 1877-1918. Included in this section are land deeds, leases, rental agreements, tax records, journals, and materials relating to water development in Orange County during the late 19th early 20th centuries. 2) The papers of Dian Rathbun Gardner, lawyer and manager of Gardner Company. These papers cover the period ca. 1920-1961, and contain materials relating to the estates of H.F. Gardner, his widow Emma Howard Gardner (d. 1935), and the setting up of the Gardner Company by the Gardner heirs following the death of Emma Gardner. 3) The papers and business records of the Gardner Company, ca. 1935-1961. These files are arranged alphabetically and include account records, employee files, some legal correspondence, etc. The company was dissolved in 1961, following the death of Dian R. Gardner.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Papers of Henri F. Gardner (Box 1).
Papers of Henri F. Gardner and Emma H. Gardner (Box 2).
Papers of Dian Rathbun Gardner and misc. (Boxes 3-4).
Gardner Company papers (Boxes 5-12).
Related Material
For further information about the background of Henri F. Gardner and the Gardner family, see History of Orange County California With Biographical Sketches.... By Samuel Armor. Los Angeles, 1921. pp. 1125 (*F 868 06A7).
Items Removed from Collection
3 photographs of South Pasadena Ostrich Farm, ca.1897.
1 photograph of Palo Alto tree, 1897.
1 photograph of Ontario, California, 1889.
All of the above were added to the Picture Collection (Collection 99). UCLA Library Special Collections.
Missing Title
Santa Ana Valley Walnut Growers Association. By-laws of incorporation. Santa Ana, 1898.
Removed for separate cataloging as local imprint.
Citrus fruit industry -- California -- Orange County -- Archives.; Family papers.; Water resources development -- California -- Orange County -- Archives.; Real estate development -- California -- Orange County -- Archives.; Gardner family--Archives.; Gardner, Dian Rathbun--Archives.; Gardner, Henri F.--Archives.; Gardner Company (Orange County, Calif.); Gardner Company (Orange County, Calif.)--Archives.
- Papers of Henri F. Gardner:, 1877-1918
  - Bank records of H.F. Gardner. (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Land development, (Leases, deeds, etc.)., 1877-1899 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes property owned by Emma H. Gardner (Mrs. H.F. Gardner).
  - Land development, 1900-1907. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes papers re estate of Margaret Eleanor Tate, 1901.
  - Land development, 1908-1918. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous papers. Cards, clippings, fragments of printed materials. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous papers. Receipts, some scattered correspondence. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous papers. Includes stock certificates, etc. Some correspondence [water]. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Papers of Henri F. Gardner and Emma H. Gardner
  - H.F. Gardner's notebooks., 1880s.; (4 vol.). (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - H.F. Gardner's notebooks., (6 vol.). (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - H.F. Gardner's taxes. State, county, city tax assesments and payments, 1883-1906. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - re estate of Henri F. Gardner. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Estate of H.F. Gardner. Operating expenditures for Emma H. Gardner. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes mortgages, receipts, repairs, etc.
  - Emma H. Gardner's taxes. State, county, city for, 1917/18-1926/27. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Taxes (continued). State, county, city for, 1927/28-1930/31. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Includes miscellaneous assesments, etc.
  - re estate of Emma Howard Gardner, 1932-. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Papers of Dian Rathbun Gardner: ca., 1920-1961
  - Notes, minutes, etc. of Gardner heirs before forming Gardner Company, 1931-January 1935. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Land development, (Leases, deeds, etc.)., 1920s. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Includes land owned by Emma H. Gardner.
  - Land development. Some correspondence. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    [Includes Gardner Company materials].
  - Liquidation of Gardner Company, [Following death of D.R. Gardner]., 1961. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous papers. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Includes Manager's report on Gardner Company, January 15, 1939; one daily notebook of D.R. Gardner; etc.
  - Orange and lemon groves. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Gardner Company check book, 1946-1947. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Papers of Dian Rathbun Gardner and Miscellaneous
  - D.R. Gardner trip diary, Mexico, Photograph album., 1950. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Photographs. Santa Ana High School diploma of D.R. Gardner, 1903. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Ephemera--examples of late 19th and early 20th century advertising. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Ephemera--scattered periodicals. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Newspapers. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Two certificates of district and circuit court practice for D.R. Gardner. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Gardner Company papers
  - Secretary Treasurer reports, 1935-1949. (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
  - Annual reports, 1935-1939. (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - Manager's reports, 1935-1942. (Box 5, Folder 7-9)
  - Accounts, 1936-1939. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Accounts, 1935-1939. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Los Angeles Property reports, 1942-1949. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Time records, 1940-1942. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Account Book--Orra G. Devereaux, ca., 1935-1955. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Bank records, 1939-1945. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Financial reports and appraisal (3)., 1946, 1954, 1959. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Farm Center. Officers Handbook. Orange County Farm Bureau, October 1936. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Fertilizers. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Gas. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Hardware. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Hay and horses. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Insurance. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Insurance. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Labor. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Laboratory work [Agricultural]. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Legal matters--Fogel and Berman, attorneys. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Lemons. (Box 8, Folder 3)
    General note
    See also: Box 3, folder 6
  - Los Angeles property. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    See also: Land Development (Box 1, folder 3-5) and Taxes (Box 11, folder 4-10 and Box 12, folder 1)
  - Los Angeles property--insurance. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Los Angeles property--labor, repairs, supplies. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Los Angeles property--Third & Flower (leases, appraisals, etc.). (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous [mostly correspondence]. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Mortgages: Citizens Trust & Savings. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Mortgages: Roland J. Giroux. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Office supplies; telephone tolls. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Oil leases (mostly Basin Oil Company). (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Orange County property--rentals, 1935-1947. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Orange County property--Florance Barnes, lots 3, 4, & 5 of Gardner's addition. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Orange County property--additions to 140 west La Veta House. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Oranges, 1927-1939. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Oranges, 1940s. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Oranges, 1940s. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Oranges--returns and refunds, (Glassell Street and Taft Avenue ranches)., 1948. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Pacific Railway Company. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Persimmons, avocadoes, limes, olives, etc. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Persimmons, avocadoes, limes, olives, etc. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Pest control, 1948. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Property--house repairs. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Real estate--letters, 1931-1941. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Social Security, unemployment insurance and taxes. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Taxes--data for and subsequent years., 1944 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Taxes--capital stock. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Taxes--federal returns, 1935-1946. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Taxes--Internal Revenue, information and rulings. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Taxes--Los Angeles and Orange City & County, 1934-1939. (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Taxes--Los Angeles and Orange City & County, 1940s. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Taxes--Miscellaneous. (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Taxes--State Corporation franchise tax returns, 1935-1938. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Tractor, 1927-1948. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Truck, 1938-1949. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Walnuts. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Water development, Orange County. (Box 12, Folder 5-7)